In addition to his private motto of, "I will work harder."
By this time, the weather had broken and the spring plowing had begun.
The shed where Snowball had drawn his plans of the windmill had been shut up,
and it was assumed that the plans had been rubbed off the floor.
Every Sunday morning at 10:00, the animals assembled in the big barn to
receive their orders for the week.
The skull of old Major, now clean of flesh, had been disinterred from the
orchard and set up on a stump at the foot of the flagstaff beside the gun.
After the hoisting of the flag, the animals were required to file past the
skull in a reverent manner before entering the barn.
Nowadays, they did not sit all together as they had done in the past.
Napoleon, with Squealer and another pig named Minimus, who had a remarkable gift
for composing songs and poems, sat on the front of the raised platform with
the nine young dogs forming a semicircle round them and the other the sitting behind.
The rest of the animals sat facing them in the main body of the barn.
Napoleon read out the orders for the week in a gruff, soldierly style, and
after a single singing of Beasts of England, all the animals dispersed.
On the third Sunday after Snowball's expulsion, the animals were somewhat
surprised to hear Napoleon announce that the windmill was to be built after all.
He did not give any reason for having changed his mind, but merely warned the
animals that this extra task would mean very hard work.
It might even be necessary to reduce their rations.
The plans, however, had all been prepared down to the last detail.
A special committee of pigs had been at work upon them for the past 3 weeks.
The building of the windmill, with various other improvements, was expected to take 2 years.
That evening, Squealer explained privately to the other animals that
Napoleon had never in reality been opposed to the windmill.
On the contrary, it was he who had advocated it in the beginning,
and the plan which Snowball had drawn on the floor of the incubator shed had
actually been stolen from among Napoleon's papers.
The windmill was, in fact, Napoleon's own creation.
"Why then?" asked somebody.
"Had he spoken so strongly against it?"
Here, Squealer looked very sly.
"That," he said, "was Comrade Napoleon's cunning.
He had seemed to oppose the windmill simply as a maneuver to get rid of
Snowball, who was a dangerous character and a bad influence.
Now that Snowball was out of the way, the plan could go forward without his interference.
This, said Squealer, was something called tactics.
He repeated a number of times, "Tactics, comrades, tactics!"
skipping round and whisking his tail with a merry laugh.
The animals were not certain what the word meant, but Squealer spoke so
persuasively, and the three dogs who